hi everybody welcome back today we're
going to do the first comparison video
for Canadian creams I think quite a lot
this will transfer over to America to uh
so what we're going to do is we're going
to make two very simple batches of
chocolate ice cream one using this which
is the same cream I used in the first
video I had to edit it out because this
I know is just bad and we're going to
also use this which is 18 coffee creamer
so if you want to see which one out of
these two low-cost brands that makes
better ice cream stick around and we'll
find out
so
why was this so bad
it's difficult to say really you know
but when you look at it 33 fat content
ingredients cream milk that's the same
as every cream
cellulose gel carrageenan and cellulose
gum
it has zero sugar
yeah it's there's not a lot else in
there really just standard lactose kind
of ingredients but
it it did not whip well
um
33 is probably as low as you want to go
for whipping cream I'm not sure this
would even hold up if you whip this and
try and keep it for any period of time
it's just going to start to separate
because the fat content's too low
I personally like 36 to 38 fat and up to
whip successfully then you don't have to
add all the stuff to it apart from maybe
a little bit of something to stabilize
it but to have the stabilizers in this
and have that many stabilizers in this
off the shelf it's not ideal for making
ice cream at all
the coffee cream now again this is just
cream so this is just 18 milk fat
uh coffee cream it does have some sugar
so it's um
one gram per 15 so one tablespoon of
cream one gram per tablespoon so we know
a tablespoon is approximately 15 grams
so it's like six and a half percent
sugar
um
there's no sugar in the actual
ingredients it's just milk cream and
sodium citrate which is
sodium salt
that's often called sour salt sodium
salt is a preservative and an emulsifier
strange enough
uh it's used in a lot of let's get this
out of the shop it's used in a lot of
foods as a preservative
it has the sour taste and a salty taste
I think actually they use it in
[Music]
they use it in soda for you know mixing
drinks that gives you that unique sour
salty kind of taste
so we're going to need to account for
the sugars in that it's only six percent
it's not a lot so what we're going to do
is we're going to make a couple of like
I said super simple chocolate ice creams
using
this
because it's all that's available in the
supermarkets where I live I've got more
coming over you know much better cocoa
powder than this stuff
but I know it's what a lot of you like
and have available to you so looking at
my notes in front of me we're going to
start with two ice cream makes using
these two creams they're all going to
have approximately 12 flat 10 milk soil
is non-fat 16 sugar content and 40
percent total solids all right so I'm
going to adjust the recipes and get as
close as I can to that I've got them
written down in front of me we're pretty
give or take 0.1 or 0.2 percent we've
got them all identical so let's knock
these two up I'm not going to bother
talking about how to make these it's not
about the recipe it's about the cream so
I'm going to knock these two up get them
in the fridge and then we'll start
churning them after that so what we've
got in here is we've got all our
ingredients for our basic but cheers
I'll tell you exactly what it is we have
310 grams of milk 225 grams of the
whipping cream 90 grams of sugar 22
grams of dextrose 29 grams of skim milk
powder 20 grams of cocoa powder at 10
fat
all right so we're just going to warm it
up
um I've got all of this in it I wouldn't
normally put the cream in but consuming
it's got so much junk in it I'm gonna
put it all in to bring up the
temperature I'm just going to warm it up
if you don't have a thermometer you're
going to warm it up to the point where
you start to get steam come off the top
of the surface at that point you know
you're around 65 70 degrees C and that's
when you want to kind of hold it there
for a minute or two once we've done that
we're going to take it off the heat and
put it in a container to chill in the
fridge
[Music]
okie dokie so this is the second ping
this is the second batch this is the 18
fat creamer so this is still this is not
the flavored
coffee creamer this is just straight
cream
um with a little bit of sugar in it but
I think it's likely
lactose rather than you know sucrose but
it doesn't say it only so who knows
um in this recipe there is a hundred
grams of milk 450 grams of the 18 cream
95 of sugar 20 of dextrose 27 are skim
milk powder and 20 of cocoa again what
we're going to do just like the last
time we're going to just warm this up
until the steam starts to come off the
top and then we're going to keep it
there for two or three minutes and then
put it in a container and chill it down
nice and quick and then it will churn
both and see which ones better
[Music]
couple of things to note doing those two
bases they're both in the freezer handle
fridge
this freezer is really nice it's got
like an automatic ice maker built into
the bottom I'm actually just able to put
the containers straight in to the ice
bath cools It Down super quick transfer
it to the fridge for the next you know
45 minutes and we're good to go but
making them on the hob the 33 whipping
cream which is Dairyland
brand that had a very unusual texture it
it you could tell it was overstabilized
already just the cream before doing
anything else and as your as you heat it
up
the base thins out and you don't get a
traditional custard thick base to it so
it's very watery this is likely down to
how they make the cream
I don't know I don't work in a Dairy but
you know I've made enough ice cream over
the years to know what is good cream
what is bad cream
um the 18 creamer and I just want to
emphasize again let me just grab it out
of the fridge
this is this creamer the Dairyland brand
it it has
the six and a half percent sugar in it
now it's not sucrose today could be
lactose could be galactose don't know
but
it has a much more traditional cream
texture it's the by heating it up it
proves it's not overstabilized because
it didn't separate at all and it's got a
thicker denser kind of feel to it yes
it's much lower in fat 18 you wouldn't
be able to whip this at 18 18 fat you
need
minimum really to to whip you can whip
32 cream but just not very well it's not
very stable at that point
um but this so far is winning out
obviously there was a lot more of this
in in the recipe 450 grams I think it
was versus 100 grams of milk
but this is to see which result makes
the best ice cream not interested in
what it is to drink or use in other
Foods ice cream this channel is about
ice cream so let's get these bases
chilled completely and we'll pop them in
the new machine see which one churns
better
okay the bases have been in the fridge
for a few hours now we're going to get
the machine fired up and get it chilled
down before we put the first one in to
churn so how do we do it remember
turn the dial
press the button and I'll be back in 10
minutes
okay this is the first one that's going
in this is the 33 whipping cream it's
got a very watery consistency like I
mentioned earlier it's improved a little
bit while sitting in the fridge but
let's just uh let's get it in churning
[Music]
about there we're gonna
turn the cooling off just for a couple
of minutes and
while I'm talking
we're going to get our cheap ass
container
I mean they're better for the
environment obviously the cardboard ones
that I usually use
you know we try and reuse them actually
um
we normally get about three to four goes
out of each one as long as you don't
break it when you're eating it
but
we've got plastic in a moment
machine off
I've been told by music that I can
actually turn this so
let's see
let's
[Music]
okay
not a lot of overrun because it's a tiny
little batch something to note in all
ice cream machines is if your base
doesn't come up to the second level of
the Dasher
you won't get a lot of overrun because
it needs that to incorporate the air as
it turns around
so you'll end up with something like 10
there's still somewhere on the machine
here so you don't have the 10 kind of
overrun at that stage so it's always
best to determine what is the right
amount of bass to put in each machine to
give the right amount of overrun but for
now this is number one
I don't have any means to identify that
this is the cheapest cream so
still one
of my daughter's stickers we're gonna go
for wax sticker there that's the one
that indicates
this is the 33 cream with all the crap
in it I'm gonna get in the freezer and
then we will churn the next one
it's the next day
I fell asleep
um we're gonna get this last mix churn
up it's
um it's the 18 percent
cream it's much better consistency
straight on the fridge
but uh
with most chocolate ice creams you
really could do with an emulsifier I
don't have any at hand so
let's get the machine chilled down and
get this one in there as well
[Music]
okay we're about ready it's uh
much better churning texturing
consistency so we're just going to give
this a minute and then we'll get this
out into our container and then pop it
in the freezer just to harden down for a
couple of hours
foreign
[Music]
thank you
two chocolate ice creams made with two
different creams and if you remember we
have our sticker which is a a unicorn
and no sticker which is the other one so
we've got 33 whipping cream with loads
of stuff added to it from the store and
then our 18
coffee creamer which has only
sodium citrate if I remember
it's like a whole other day
I don't have my normal bowl
it's not arrived yet so we're gonna
take our new scoop our zero zero long
[Music]
let me just give it a quick wash
okie dokie let's
get some scooped up into the Oni Bowl I
have that is reasonable
and
see which one turned out the best
[Music]
it doesn't look great
looks much better looks much smoother
Okay so
whipping 33 whipping cream 18 coffee
creamer in that order so I'll put a
little thing up on the screen let me get
into the middle I'll put a little thing
up on screen show that this one is the
33 whipping cream and this one is the
coffee creamer
ah let's see
the whipping cream broke apart when I
put the spoon in
stranger has the effect of being too low
and solids the the recipes are identical
so the fat percentage sugar solids
Etc are identical waving spring around
um
it's it's quite
unusual texture it's
it's quite icy
um
doesn't have a good mouthfeel
actually UK single cream did this does
this
um
it's something to do with the the makeup
of the actual cream itself
okay on to the 18 fat
coffee creamer
it spoons much nicer like much more
traditional doesn't break apart
smoother
much nicer ice
Crystal size
very very smooth on the tongue
for an unstabilized ice cream
that's okay I mean it tastes like
Hershey's but
so much better than that whipping cream
they're night and day different it's the
coffee creamer is just a smooth ice
cream it's thicker base when heating it
up making it on hob
churned much more traditionally
as the the correct kind of texture that
you'd expect
it's smoother to scoop it it doesn't
fall apart it's nicer on the tongue
I'd be happy with that it's not perfect
but I'll be happy with that whereas the
whipping cream is is kind of dry
um
which can be a result of of two higher
solids but that's not the reason here
very cold
which means there's too much free water
considering the recipes are identical
that shouldn't be the case
if you put stabilizers in it
this one will probably be okay because
this one just had sodium citrate in it
and it would probably take that
stabilizer quite well
this one I don't I don't know what it
would do but
I do know what it would do
um
a day and night different so at the
Dairyland brand the 33 whipping cream
versus the 18 coffee creamer
the 18 coffee creamer wins hands down
we're gonna
keep the ice cream in the freezer we're
going to work on the next comparison
video which is going to be the Lucerne
brand cream
and
we'll see how they compare then we can
compare all of these things in the last
video the third video where we get out
the big boys the luxury creams so thanks
very much for watching don't forget to
like And subscribe and we'll see you
next week for the next Canadian cream
comparison video
[Music]